<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short plea for the common-wealth, in this monstrous and shaking juncture, wherein treason is scarcely accounted an offence, and traitors have so manie advocates. Published for the safetie of the state, and the undeceiving of the people, by a friend to justice and the common-wealth. The second edition reviewed, and enlarged in manie particulars. It is better one man should perish, then the whole bee destroied.</title>
            <author>Friend to Justice and the Common-wealth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93219</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866357</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118628</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961694</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E790_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207299</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866357</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866357e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118628)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 120:E790[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short plea for the common-wealth, in this monstrous and shaking juncture, wherein treason is scarcely accounted an offence, and traitors have so manie advocates. Published for the safetie of the state, and the undeceiving of the people, by a friend to justice and the common-wealth. The second edition reviewed, and enlarged in manie particulars. It is better one man should perish, then the whole bee destroied.</title>
                  <author>Friend to Justice and the Common-wealth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du-Gard, printer to the Council of State.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini, 1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 29"; "Let both be Jn".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118628:1"/>
            <p>A SHORT PLEA FOR THE Common-wealth, IN This monstrous and shaking Juncture, wherein <hi>Treason</hi> is scarcely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an offence, and <hi>Traitors</hi> have so manie Advocates.</p>
            <p>Published for the Safetie of the State, and the undeceiving of the people, by a friend to Justice and the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>The second Edition reviewed, and enlarged in manie particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is better one man should perish, then the whole bee destroied.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Becaus sentence against an evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of men is fully set in them to do evil.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Eccles 8.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>But let none of you suffer as a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, or as a thief, or as an evil doer, or as a busie-bodie in other men's matters.
<bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 4.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For if I build again the things that I have destroyed, I make my self a Transgressor.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 2.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Du-Gard,</hi> Printer to the Council of State. <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118628:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118628:2"/>
            <head>A SHORT PLEA FOR THE Common-wealth, &amp;c. Discovering the Treasonable practices of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg> LOVE and his Confederates against it.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T griev's mee exceedingly, that the desperate follie and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of this age (wherein men account <hi>Treason</hi> a virtue, and, to solicite for <hi>Traitors,</hi> Pietie and Religion) should enforce my pen to paper, especially at this time, when the blood of the manie thousands shed since this last Engagement in <hi>Scotland</hi> (so fresh in memorie) the Armies beeing ready again to engage upon the same quarrel, and the safetie of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth so desperately endangered with the black at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of a cruel War (the sad effects of these Treasons) call's rather to all honest men to gird their swords on their thighs, and prevent the destruction that is at the door, then to seek the diverting of Justice, and the execution thereof upon the convict Instruments of this miserable Calamitie; whom the verie finger of God hath pointed out by a providential discoverie beyond exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for whose <hi>Treason,</hi> the High Court of Justice hath sentenc't one of them to death; and whose <hi>Impunitie</hi> will bee the greatest blow to the safetie of the Common-wealth that it yet hath received. The serious consideration whereof hath alarmed my heart, and as the dumb childe somtime spake when hee saw one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118628:3"/>going to kill his father, so am I enforced to crie out, <hi>Men, brethren, and Fathers' bring not upon your selvs the blood of the War in Scotland,</hi> and do not by such Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents destroy the safetie of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>The question now is not whether the mercie of the State should bee extended to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Love,</hi> who is found guiltie of raising this War in Scotland, and who hath stouted it out to the utmost at the High Court of Justice; and in his Petition to the Parlament for his life, not owning the Laws, by which hee was judged, to bee the Laws of the Land, or such as were just, but <hi>[your]</hi> Laws: (an imparallel'd piece of contumacie, and which never in the like case anie dared to present to the Parlament) I say, the question is not, whether the mercie of the State should bee extended to M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Love,</hi> becaus a godlie man, a Minister, and hath formerly served the Parlament; but whether mercie should not bee first exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the State for its safetie (which hath been from its very birth designed to destruction by intestine plots and Treasons multiplied upon it, and by open Wars (in which M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Love</hi> appear's to bee a principal actor, and hee and his Confederates a chief caus of these engagements of blood and mischief) whether the blood of the manie thousands shed already in these designs ought not to bee expiated? whether the bowels of compassion towards the lives of the manie hundreds of thousands of innocent persons, and the very beeing of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth and Nation, (which no man knows but this War may burie in its grave, and put to a period) should not bee exercised, whether the foundations of Government, and the Principles on which the being of humane society do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, which these mens Practices do utterly overthrow, should not bee preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and may not challenge from this State in the first place it's tenderness and compassion, and Justice upon the heads of those whose principles and practices have laid the Ax to the root of this Government, put the safety thereof to that great hazard it is in at this day, shed the bloud of those that have been slain in this Scottish Engagement, laid the foundation and so far assisted the proceeds of this war, which may terminate this Nation, and do overthrow the Principles of humane society? and whether any man may bee so prodigal of the safety of the Common-wealth, as to lay such Presidents of favor and compassion, so bold with the Laws of the Land and the Justice of the State, as to endeavour to put by the Execution thereof, and with the bloud of those that have been slain, ruin'd and suffred the other miseries of this war, as to hinder what the Word of God, and the Law of this Nation doth require? I am sure the late King, which was called <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> &amp; in whom the Administration of Justice in this Nation som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time did reside, was not own'd in such unwarranted practices, as to protect offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from Justice, and to destroy the safety of the People whom he should protect: but for so doing had Justice executed upon himself as a Traitor by this present Parlament: in which Eminent and Impartial act the foundation of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was established, and according to which president, wee trust the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118628:3"/>will make their future proceedings, Justice and Righteousness beeing that which indeed exalt's a Nation.</p>
            <list>
               <head>But that I may not seem to beat the aër, and lay this discours without any bottom, let the Reader bee pleas'd to consider briefly</head>
               <item n="1">I. <hi>What the</hi> Treasons <hi>hinted at are, and the effects of them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="2">II. <hi>How far they concern M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  </hi> Love, <hi>and his demeanor upon Examination, Trial, Sentence, and his Application to the Parlament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="3">III. <hi>What Partie this case respect's, their deportment</hi> ab initio, <hi>their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, number, opportunities, and principles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item n="4">IV. <hi>The danger of the Common-wealth as to all.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>For the <hi>Treasons,</hi> they are no less then <hi>a Combination with the Scots,</hi> and <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> Son to the late Tyrant, to bring him in as King of England; for which purpose the Scots upon the Execution of the late King, send to the Traytors concern'd herein, that they intend to apply themselvs to the King, wherein they will consider the Presbyterian party here as themselvs; that the foundation of the Agreement should bee the Covenant; desire a constant cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondency and good understanding between those here and in Scotland. This occasioned the first meetings of these Traitors here, where the gracious disposition of the Prince was mentioned, how that Loialty and the sens of these sufferings engaged them to attempt somthing on his behalf, if so bee hee would close with the Scots and take the Covenant; and which produced the first treaty, at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Treaty bringing forth nothing, the King of Scots send's to these here, to assure them, that if they could obtein another Treaty between him and the Scots, and the Scots to moderate their Propositions, hee would give satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Scots, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Hereupon these send to the Scots to make another application to the King, and to moderate their Propositions.</p>
               <p>The Scots return, that they would make another Application to the King, but it should bee on the same terms, the former breach at the Hague occasioning rather the heightning of their Propositions, then the moderating thereof, but adviseth these to make use of their Interest with the King to give them satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Nor was the Countess of <hi>Carlile</hi> [that Mistress of Treasons] idle in these correspondencies.</p>
               <p>Hereupon these meet, consider of, conclude, and send a Petition to the King, Letters to the Queen, <hi>Jermin</hi> and <hi>Percy,</hi> to perswade the King to give the Scots satisfaction.</p>
               <p>These return, that however things seemed to them, yet the King was resolved
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118628:4"/>to give the Scots satisfaction; and to that end a Treaty was appointed at Jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey, and <hi>Percy</hi> advised these to send one from hence to the Treaty: and moreover, that if the King and his Privy Council could not agree there, hee would remove the Treaty to Breda, and at last cast himself upon the Scot's Commissioners.</p>
               <p>Accordingly an Agent was considered of, and concluded <hi>(viz.)</hi> Capt. <hi>Titus,</hi> who was sent from these to Jersey, and an hundred pound raised amongst them to bear his charges, where hee spake with the said King; and <hi>Liberton</hi> the Scot's Commissioner, told him from what Party hee was sent from England, represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Presb. party considerable, had assurance &amp; a Letter from the King to the Ministers, and Presbyterian party here, that he would give satisfaction to the Scots, that to that end the Treaty was removed to Breda, whither hee adviseth them to send Commissioners, and that hee took notice of their non-compliance with the present Power.</p>
               <p>The Treaty being ended, <hi>Titus</hi> hearing that the Council of State understood that hee had been at Jersey, durst not go for England, but send's a Letter among other things for one to com to him at Callaïs, to receiv the Account of his Agencie.</p>
               <p>Upon the reading whereof, these here agree and send Major <hi>Alford</hi> to Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laïs, who having received of <hi>Titus</hi> the account of Transactions, returned, and to these persons that sent him give's the relation thereof; the Copy of the King's Letter aforesaid (the Original being sent to <hi>Bunce</hi> in Holland for fear of miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage) <hi>Titus</hi> his Narrative also in writing, which were all of them then Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated; also that <hi>Titus</hi> was in debt, having borrowed some money of <hi>Jermin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This occasioned the drawing of a Commission, enabling the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of Parham, Alderman <hi>Bunce,</hi> Maj. Gen. <hi>Massey,</hi> Capt. <hi>Titus</hi> to treat in the name of the Presbyterian partie in Engl. with the King at Breda, and to assist their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Scots: and when it was moved by som what power they had to send a Commission, it was answered, the King had sent to them so to do, and they had also many secluded members, whose Autority they look'd upon better then those at Westminster; which, together with Instructions thereunto annex't, were sent by <hi>Mason</hi> the Lord <hi>Percy</hi>'s servant, who came hither on purpose to give the King of Scots an Account of proceedings, and at Graves-end had those papers brought him by three of the Correspondents.</p>
               <p>Letters also were drawn and sent to the <hi>Queen, Percy, Jermin,</hi> Lord <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, Massey, Bunce</hi> &amp;c. to forward the Agreement, and to act as Authorized; and <hi>Titus</hi> had more money.</p>
               <p>And now the Business beeing put into a fair way of issue, Private Fasts are by them appointed to pray for a blessing on the Treaty, and for the continuation of the Agreement afterwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Percy</hi> write's to them to lend 10000 l to the King, which would add much
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118628:4"/>to the Agreement, and one Minister moved a way by which it might bee rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Ministers to move their friends, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>, <hi>you shall give mee</hi> 20, 30, 40, 50 l. &amp;c. <hi>for a charitable use, but you shall not ask mee wherefore;</hi> but becaus they were not assured of the King's giving satisfaction, it was forborn.</p>
               <p>This Treatie produced the end endeavored; the King send's his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to several of the Ministers, that, if they could not live quietly here, they should com to him: 3 or 4 also hee desired might bee his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, and give's instructions to his Gen. Agent M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Cook</hi> to treat them civilly, to give Letters to them, and the Presbyterians in the Citie of London from him, and to press them to action.</p>
               <p>The Scots having got the King into their hands, prepare, as they had promised at <hi>Breda,</hi> to rais Arms to put him in the throne of England, but nor <hi>Massey, Titus,</hi> nor the English were considered, whose Interest in the Presbyterian partie in England was made use of to bring the King and them together.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Massey</hi> &amp;c. complain's of to these here, who very ill resented it, and thereupon send's a long Letter to the Kirk and State complaining thereof, attributing it to their pride, laying open in what condition they were in, this with much more was wrote in sack in a table-book and sent thither.</p>
               <p>The fight at Dunbar follow's: after which rout, the Scots court this partie again; the Kirk, and State, and <hi>Massey,</hi> write by sea and land to those here, signifie the caus of the rout, advise them to stand fast to the Caus and Covenant, desire monie and 3 or 5000 muskets and case of Pistols; for monie also <hi>Massey</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> particularly pressed to, becaus of their wants.</p>
               <p>The Correspondents aforesaid considered of this Letter, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at present to rais about 300 l to send to <hi>Massey</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> which the Correspondents performed by 10 l. 5 l. a man &amp;c, A Letter was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so returned to the Kirk, and State, and <hi>Massey</hi> by these here.</p>
               <p>Upon this the Correspondencies began to have life again; and the Scot's preparations to bee in the field were signified hither, advise also to those here to caution, stedfastness, timeing of a partie seasonably here; to write to the Kirk for union, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>These return the same Cautions, advise <hi>Massey</hi> to take heed how hee came into England, and that hee bring with him a strong partie.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118628:5"/>
               <p>Returns also com from Scotland of the receits of the mony, and the Letters to the Kirk and State before-mentioned, how seasonable it was, how much union it affected, broke the designs of the advers partie, and how considerable it made them.</p>
               <p>Waies of setling intelligence by land were also signified and made use of.</p>
               <p>At length in March last came an answer to what was signified in sack in the table-book aforesaid by Col. <hi>Bampfield's</hi> man, which gave an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the state of Scotland; Letters also came in the said packet from M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Bayly</hi> (their former Correspondent in the behalf of the Kirk) and from the Lords <hi>Belcarris, Argyle, Loudoun,</hi> and <hi>Lothian</hi> wishing these here to give credit to <hi>Bampfield's</hi> negotiation, becaus hee was a Cavalier, press for 5 or 10000 l in monie to buie Arms to furnish, &amp; ships to bring over 5000 old souldiers, propose's a General to bee chosen by these here, and promise repaiement when God shall bless their endeavors so as to caus a free Parlament in England: the Agent was returned with monie in his pocket, and a Bill of Exchange to <hi>Bampfield,</hi> whose designs at large, upon what place in England, and by whom the men were to bee furnished, Cap. <hi>Titus</hi>'s Letters, brought by his man to the Lord Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors for <hi>England</hi> then at the Hague, do speak at large.</p>
               <p>Presently upon this Packet to them from <hi>Bampfeild, Cook</hi> was taken, Capt. <hi>Potter</hi> one of the Correspondents imprisoned, <hi>Titus</hi>'s Letters brought in by his man, and afterward som others were apprehended, which put a stop to their Proceedings.</p>
               <p>Then the verie relation, (which is truth in every particular) there need's no other demonstration of the dangerousness of this <hi>Treason;</hi> and the <hi>effect</hi> thereof, the present war in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and what hath and may ensue thereupon: For, nor would the King have trusted the Scot, nor the Scot medled with the King to put him in his Father's dominions, but that the Influence of this third partie in <hi>England</hi> warm'd them thereunto, and this, were it needfull, would bee largely demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated.</p>
               <p>Nor is it amiss to hint a word of the private and subtle transaction of these designs.</p>
               <p>The chief correspondents of <hi>this Form</hi> now discovered (for there is <hi>another</hi> above them, which one time or other the world will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118628:5"/>were men tenaciously fixt to the design upon a pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientious and a religious Principle, having the Ministers also in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est admiration, many of them Souldiers, and who had once served in the Army.</p>
               <p>Their meetings were upon pretence of religious Exercises; the places either in shops of Commerce, or Minister's studies.</p>
               <p>The waie of communicating the design by waie of news; seldom anie Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters produced in their Originals but by Copies, and that mostly in Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, which for som time were kept in a Book; the person from whom it came as seldom asked, that beeing generally known; nor were anie to enquire of names, the Letters and Papers also were before hand put under a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stick.</p>
               <p>The Contribution of monie was under the pretext of charitable uses; for the widdows and Orphanes, a poor distressed Gentleman beyond the Seas, this monie brought in bags or papers, laid down in ware-houses, studies and Chambers, but nothing said, nor anie seen to receiv it.</p>
               <p>And the better to accomplish their ends, another Generation of men were trained up at a Club, where they were instructed as occasion served by som of the Cabinet-Council, that they might serv their ends; All which doth exceedingly advance the goodness of God in the discoverie of these works of darkness, and therein shewing his tender care of this Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>For what M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> is concerned herein (to saie nothing of what prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Titus</hi> his going to <hi>Jersey) Titus</hi> Letter signifying his fearfulness to com to England, and desiring one to bee sent to <hi>Callais</hi> to receiv an account of his Negotiation at <hi>Jersey,</hi> was read in his hous, where hee was present with divers others; and where they concluded to send one thither to <hi>Titus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The person that was sent to <hi>Titus</hi> and returned, gave an account of his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in Mr <hi>Love's</hi> studie, where Mr <hi>Love</hi> was present and manie others; and where was read <hi>Titus</hi>'s Narration, in waie of a Diarie of proceedings at <hi>Jersey,</hi> the Copie of the King's Letter, as is mentioned before, there the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, Instructions, Letters before mentioned, were read, debated, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; and when som debate was had, concerning what autoritie they had to send a Commission, beeing single persons, and it was answered, the King having sent to them so to do, was Autoritie sufficient; M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> said, Com, com, let it go.</p>
               <p>Their Letters were read, which were agreed to bee sent to <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon <hi>Massie's</hi> complaint of neglect in <hi>Scotland,</hi> there the Letters from <hi>Massie,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of Estates, Gen. Assemblie, were read after the fight at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> which desired monie, assistance, Arms. There M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> pressed for the raising of monie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118628:6"/>upon those letters <hi>(viz.)</hi> four or five hundred pounds, saying, That if they could not rais it themselvs, they must with their friends; and spake to som to lend on that account, fignifying the contents of the Letter, for monie, Arms, &amp;c. and from whom; the summe beeing brought down to about three hundred pounds; there som of the monie was brought in, and laid down in his room, where hee was present; there som of the fasts aforesaid were kept, and hee officiated at the same Fasts at other places. There the packet from <hi>Bampfield</hi> was read, having a Letter (L) on it; the Letters also therein from the Lords <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carris, Loudoun, Argyle,</hi> and M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Baylie,</hi> moving for five or ten thousand pounds for the furnishing of Arms, and shipping for five thousand old souldiers, to bee brought from beyond the Sea; the time when it should bee repai'd, and moving for a Gen. to bee nominated by them for those men; there fourtie pound was thought convenient by him and others, to bee sent to <hi>Bampfeild;</hi> ten pounds to <hi>Bampfeild's</hi> man was paid, and thirtie pounds by Bill of Exchange, sent to <hi>Bampfeild,</hi> and a Letter wrote with (B) on it, brought to Captain <hi>Potter</hi> for <hi>Bampfield,</hi> and said by the partie that left it at <hi>Potter's,</hi> that it came from Mr <hi>Love;</hi> Mr <hi>Love</hi> and another beeing before spoke to draw up the Letter, and at all these meetings and transactions Mr <hi>Love</hi> was present, discoursed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated at them; and at several other meetings also at his hous, concerning the same designs, which I shall not now add, becaus I suppose a full narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive thereof will bee published to the world, and I intend this for no other then a short account of what was deposed against Mr <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor shall I summ this up together, or draw from it conclusions that will naturally arise, leaving that to the Reader's Observation, it lying so plainly; onely I shall leav it to the Reader's Judgment, Whether M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love's</hi> appearing in the substantial part of this design, as is before mentioned at large, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a messenger is sent to <hi>Titus</hi> their Agent, his Negotiation received, the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, debateing, and concluding of a Commission, and Instructions to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to treat with the King at Breda; Monie rais'd, Letters sent and received from <hi>Scotland</hi> for Ammunition, &amp;c. and other correspondencies, even to <hi>March</hi> last, do not intitle him to the first part thereof, (if not to his privitie then, yet) to his consenting afterward? Nay, who can believ that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> would join in the bodie, and most dangerous parts of the design, and not bee first informed (if hee knew it not before, which I have reason to believ hee did) what had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded? or, How can it bee supposed, that a rational man would have to do in the middle of a business, of the beginning of which hee was ignorant? espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a Minister, who hath or ought to have more then ordinarie wariness in things of that nature? howëver, hee that entreth into the substantial part of a design, is legally included in the whole, and then whether hee bee not guiltie of the whole transaction, which hath produced the war in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and which war hee hath abetted and assisted?</p>
               <p>For his <hi>demeanor</hi> from the time of his first examination to this daie, I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118628:6"/>had rather burie in silence (beeing so unlike a man, a Minister and a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) then to discover to the world his infirmities, and indeed shall not make that my work, farther then is necessarie to the point of safetie, and therein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what I first proposed.</p>
               <p>At his Examination hee made such a deep and general profession of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, (though the proof and his confession at the Court contradicted it) that the Committee were at a stand how to ask such an Innocent Professor anie question of Guilt; hee also said, Ask mee anie question concerning my self, and I will ingenuously answer you, but when such questions came to touch, beeing according to the Informations of Treasons against him, hee refused to answer as to what concern'd himself before Evidence was produced; or what concerned others, saying, That hee would not bee an Informer, though the old Law of <hi>England</hi> require's that a Traitor answer <hi>Yea</hi> or <hi>No,</hi> and that hee disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver other Traitors also; nor would hee sign his Examination, whereto hee had made som denial.</p>
               <p>When hee came to the Barr,
<note place="margin">That hee did give M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Jekiel</hi> 5 l. towards the 30 l. for <hi>Bampfield,</hi> and 10 shillings to Cap. <hi>Potter,</hi> for <hi>Stirk,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> Agent; the former of which, though not sworn at Court, yet hath since been with grief of spirit acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel;</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much troubled that hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in that particular, did of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord confess it.</note> Hee made three dreadfull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testations, before God, Angels, and men; That hee never wrote Letter to the King, Queen, <hi>Jermin, Percie, Titus, Massey,</hi> &amp;c. That hee never received Letter from any of them; That hee never contributed any monie, nor gathered any for the King, &amp;c. or <hi>Massey, Titus,</hi> &amp;c. which desperate prevarication, if there were no more said, is enough to convince every serious man of the falsitie of his heart. Though it is not proved that hee wrote Letters with his own hand, yee hee heard the Letters read that were sent, and consented to their going to <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. Though it is not proved that hee received any Letters with his own hand (though that from <hi>Bampfield</hi> endorsed <hi>(L)</hi> carried and read in his Hous, may easily bee beleeved to bee directed to himself) yet hee was present at the reading of them; and pressed the answering of the contents of som of them as to monie, &amp;c. Though it is not proved that hee contributed any monie with his own hand, and gathered it for the uses aforesaid, yet it is proved that hee press'd at the meetings in his Hous for the raising of monie, and that of considerable summes, spoke to particular men so to do, and part of the monie was brought and left in his Hous in his presence. And hereby let any sober man judg of his spirit, and the truth of what hee would affirm. Every ordinarie understanding know's, that a man write's when hee consent's to write, receive's when hee agree's to what is received, especially where many are joyn'd in the advice, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118628:7"/>what is sent, and received. Parlaments, Councils, other Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, so write, so receiv, either by their Secretarie, or another person: And thus M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> know's hee did write, hee did receiv, hee did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute; and yet that hee might delude God, Angels, and men, (but the former will not bee mockt) hee com's forth with these knowing falshoods and Prevarications, not only at first, but at last, before his sentence, where hee would have pinn'd that lie upon the hearts of all the Spectators, after the proof had passed, and himself confess'd that many meetings were at his Hous, where som such things as were mentioned in the charge were read and debated, particularly where the Commission in the name of the Presbyterian Partie in <hi>England,</hi> autorizing the Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> &amp;c. was read, it beeing in his studie. I tremble to think what a reckoning this will amount to, when God shall let M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> see what hee hath don.</p>
               <p>M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> would have denied the jurisdiction of the Court, if he had not remembred what it cost his Master <hi>Charls,</hi> against whose Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> is, as well as that Tyrant was; then hee pleaded (when there was no remedie) <hi>not guiltie,</hi> behaving himself exceeding haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, prevaricating uncivilly, which reached not onlie the witnesses, but the Atturnie-General, the Council for the State, the Council of State, and the Court: would acknowledg nothing; no: hee said, Hee would die before hee would accuse any man; and said, Hee would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to no question. In his defens hee presented his Innocencie, and his Principles, <hi>(viz.)</hi> wholly contrary to the present Government; and, with what Rhetorick and Argument hee could, endeavored to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade the people and confirm them in the same opinion; What hee had don (hee said) was according to the Covenant, and in simplicitie of heart, though before hee had confes't what is above mentioned (his ingenuitie beeing only to acknowledg what was clearly proved, for which the State will not thank him:) Hee said, that it was according to his Judgment and Conscience, that Religion and Liberty would bee more advanc't by the King's coming in by the Scots then by the Irish, (so that hee should com in one way or other, was his Judgment and Conscience; but rather by the Scots, and by the Scots the King is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring it, which hath produced this war,) and hee said, that the Covenant lead him to pray for the Union of both Nations, and the <hi>Scots</hi> having chosen the King, to pray for him, and against Incendiaries; also
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118628:7"/>that his Principles were according to the Vows &amp; Declarations of both Houses of Parliament, (yet those verie Vows and Declarations will not own that malignant interest that M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> and his brethren in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> have now taken in) and for such an unquestionable Autoritie hee is willing to adventure as before; that if the ends of the first War had been kept, it would have been more for the glorie, peace, and honor of the Nation. Becaus in his private opinion they are not kept (though wee can make it appear, that what hee stumble's at is most sutable to the ends of the first warr, <hi>viz. Safetie</hi> and <hi>Libertie</hi>) must hee therefore endeavor another warr in times of peace? Hee saith, that doing Acts of justice upon Political accounts, though the matter of Fact were true, is not justice, but murther; instancing (but most falsly) in the case of <hi>Jehu;</hi> then threaten's the Court, that if they take away his life, they will shed innocent bloud, and God will require it at their hands.</p>
               <p>When the Sentence was com to bee given, hee continued as before, would have had his confessions of concealment to bee only misprision of Treason; excepted against the witnesses, and protested that hee knew no designs, or persons designing in <hi>England</hi> or out of <hi>England,</hi> nor the place where, or the time when anie invasions will bee made on this Nation; and after Sentence, that God and his Conscience condemn'd him not.</p>
               <p>Since the receiving of his Sentence, in his Petition to the Parlament for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, hee offer's, not to compensate his offenses, by his discovering what hee knew of the Traitors in the same confederacie, though hee had confessed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before his Sentence but what was proved, nor all that neither; and since his sentence, his future testimonie is invalid, nor doth hee acknowledg the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie or the Laws by which hee was judged, to bee the Laws of the Land, but by <hi>[Your]</hi> Laws I am justly condemned; which his brother M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Calamie</hi> instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in, on <hi>Mundaie</hi> last in the Tower, perhaps to put M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> out of all hope of mercie, that his good tricks, and the rest of his close Brethren, might not com to light, and so M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi>'s head might burie their walkings in the dark; <hi>But God is a consuming fire, and hee will bring everie work to judgment.</hi> By all what hath been said, doth plainly appear, that as M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi>'s Treasons against this State, were don out of judgment and conscience, and according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: so even to this daie, hee remain's of the same opinion; which principle, how dangerous it is to the Common-wealth, upon comparing the present ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof in this war, and what sadder issues it may have, is easie to judg. And how can hee exspect mercie of that Common-wealth, whose Laws hee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118628:8"/>hath broken in so high a manner? whose safetie hee hath so much endangered? and yet refuseth to own its Autoritie as the Ordinance of God for good, or to submit unto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>For the Partie this case respect's, it run's through generally the whole Ministerie of the Nation, and that not so much those that are in Wolvs cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the Angels of Light, men of great repute for godliness, religion, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, activitie for the Parlament; who have so great opportunities by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, such influences as the Oracles of God, as the very Scripture; they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stributed throughout all <hi>England,</hi> engaging people, speaking to thousands at a time from several parts, which none others have, upon a religious tie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science and the Covenant, to exstirpate this Government, and blowing up the turbulent breasts of all discontented persons, to burn this Common-wealth, and themselvs; and how far they have prevailed herein, and what mischief it hath produced, the present face of affairs will evince.</p>
               <p>These are they, that, when with one heart and hand wee were following the common enemie, made the first division, upon the account of their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; this set deserving men against deserving men; and those that yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daie were like Brothers, jointly brandishing their swords against a common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, are now readie to run their swords in one anothers bowels. It would bee endless to reckon up, how dissenters from them, who had more Scripture for their practice then Presbyterie, and as much or more merit to plead for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, then the others, were turn'd out of the places of trust, both Civil and Militarie, how the new <hi>Model,</hi> notwithstanding all their faithfulness and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, was endeavored to bee broke; how the Armie was first ordered to lie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Oxford,</hi> when the <hi>Scots,</hi> who were appointed to wait on the King, retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Westmorland;</hi> what workings there were to bring in the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> again upon the head of the Armie, and the Scot's Armie to effect it, which his sudden death prevented; what <hi>Shibboleths</hi> were made? what consultations had to destroie them? witness the Ordinance against blasphemie, &amp;c. What endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors to break the Armie, and leaving <hi>Ireland</hi> in its blood, that it might serv as a check to the Armie, for which end my Lord <hi>Lisle</hi> was remaunded, after the expence of a 100000 pounds for his expedition, assoon almost as his foot was set on that Island, and delivering all into the power of <hi>Inchiqueen,</hi> who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gave it to the King, and what it had like to have cost, let the season, when nothing but <hi>Dublin</hi> remained in the Parlament's power, and that close besieged, speak; for the successes there, and in <hi>England,</hi> these people would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praie for, nor give thanks, looking upon them as Judgments.</p>
               <p>It would require a volume to discours how Regiments, pretended for <hi>Ireland,</hi> were kept a year about on the Countrie, on pretence of wanting opportunitie of transportation, but intended to ballance or break the Armie, how the breach of the Armie was endeavored, how they were voted Traitors, but upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of an humble Petition, that was said to bee amongst them; and then part
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118628:8"/>of them were ordered for <hi>Ireland</hi> under other Officers, not in mercie or relief for that Countrie, (for som chief Officers declared, that they intended no such thing) but to destroie the Armie: M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Nichols</hi> said, the Ministers put them on this against the Armie, making it no less then damnation to send schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks into <hi>Ireland;</hi> and then, how were Garrisons emptied of friends to the Armie? som dismantled, where such persons were Governors; the Militia, and other Arms, Ammunition, and Artillerie seiz'd; that it might bee treason for anie to touch them; afterwards the Irish Regiments ordered to bee drawn up against the Armie, and had put an end to all, had not God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented to admiration, in raising up the hearts of the Souldier at <hi>Triple-heath:</hi> After this, a companie of Boies were raised and encouraged to put force upon the Hous, which was the first and unparallel'd affront that ever was put on them; an Armie upon that raised in <hi>London,</hi> and the Citie fortified, which brought forth a new War; after that a Treatie must bee had with the King, and the <hi>Scot's</hi> Armie com into <hi>England</hi> (though <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s hand onely made it an unlawful thing, for 'twas not an <hi>Invasion,</hi> but what <hi>hand</hi> should effect it was the question) the Lords would not declare against it, the Citie Petition for it, the Hous of Commons staggering whether the <hi>Scots</hi> should bee voted Enemies or no; even when the Lord General <hi>Cromwel</hi> was drawn forth to sight them, the Navie was then broken, which is not recovered to this daie.</p>
               <p>Cap. <hi>Batten</hi> petitioned to bee Vice-Admiral, who had before that time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Commission from the Prince; the <hi>militia</hi> unsetled, though insurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were everie where; and when granted, through the importunitie of manie, yet gave not power to kill and slaie; and though that insurrections were everie where, <hi>Hamilton</hi> and others in the field for the King, about 100000 that sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, yet none of them stirr'd to repel them, though our Forces fought most<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 2000 to 10000, and that from Pembroke to Edinborough; then by a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie all was endeavored to bee effected, and the King's Concessions voted in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to peace, and the Armie intended to have been voted Traitors, and then the Hous to adjourn to accomplish force by the King and their own partie to have destroied the <hi>Armie,</hi> (who are mentioned so often here, not barely as an <hi>Armie,</hi> but as they keep and own their first Principles, and the true interest of Libertie and Safetie) and the honest Interest, and all by a partie on whom their Influence so far prevailed to act those things; and when God put by all their mischievous intents, brought Justice on the King, and chang'd the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment through much mercie, they fall presently point blanck into the King's Interest, and plot, and contrive the destruction thereof, through the Treasons now brought by the finger of God to light, and which are shortly touched before; and upon the Armies march into Scotland took off the former Lord General <hi>Fairfax</hi> from keeping his Commission, thereby hoping to hinder (at least) our timely march to that Countrie; and to these you may add the Lords, and manie thousand other persons who did gallantly in their generation,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118628:9"/>whom these men's violence, becaus they cannot lord it over State and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, have led into a general disaffection to this present Autoritie, whom they have entitled to the Malignant Caus, and laid the Guilt theerof upon their shoulders, and all upon the Account of Religion and the Covenant; which had I time I should answer to the full. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love's</hi> blood run's through these men's veins, his Principles are theirs, and who exspect his success in this trial as an incouragement, or disheartning to their future treasonable proceedings.</p>
               <p>And here it is will not bee amiss, briefly to consider what hath been the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment</hi> of the persons against whom they have thus proceeded, and of the <hi>State,</hi> as to all.</p>
               <p>When this generation of men (upon no substantial caus in Reason or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) had prevailed with the Earls of <hi>Essex, Manchester,</hi> and S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>William Waller,</hi> to turn these men out of their Armies, Brigades, Garrisons; and with the <hi>Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by the Citie Remonstrance, out of all Civil Imploiments, at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time when the enemie had stripped manie of them of all their estates, and had not bread to live upon; when they endeavored also to destroie their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons for their consciences, (which with meekness they offred to manifest, was regulated, according to the word of God) and for that end were bold to break the Privileges of <hi>Parlament,</hi> and afterwards obtained the Ordinance against Heresie, &amp;c. that so what the enemie had left, their sword might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroie, and what would not wrack their Consciences, should reach their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; and this drove on by som of this conspiracie, who had such hardned bowels, that they refus'd to afford anie relief to those pretious souls, who had brought them up from their Cradles, and out of their estates given them mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and beeing; What was then the demeanor of these Sectaries (as they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them)? was it in Treasons and Rebellions, railing against the Magistrate, falling in with the malignant Interest? &amp;c. or was it not in all meekness, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and silence? not a whisperer so much, much less a treason, was thought or spoke of.</p>
               <p>When God was pleased to call those out-casts together in the New Model, did they refuse to do this work, though things were then at a verie low ebb? or to venture their lives? or did they not (through the goodness of God) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complish such a swift deliverance, that it made the former war to bee almost forgotten, notwithstanding all the endeavors by contrarie orders, dividing the Armie, laying them with inconsiderable numbers before Garrisons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were masters of the Field (witness the first <hi>Oxford</hi>-Leagure when the Scots retreated, or rather ran away, Scot-like, to Westmorland) the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> taken from the Armie, and 2500 of their best hors to join with the Scots; the Armie unpaid, and unrecruited? &amp;c. I saie, when after all this they were designed to bee broken, the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> to bee put in the head of them for that end, &amp;c. did they take upon them such a ranting spirit as these men (though they were able to do what they would) or set themselvs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118628:9"/>to break those, who unworthily endeavored to break them in pieces as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for their service? or rather did they not laie their mouths unto the dust, and were contented after all to have lived in banishment, rather then by the <hi>Parlament</hi> to bee thought inconsistent with the peace of the Nation?</p>
               <p>When the pretended design for <hi>Ireland</hi> was on foot, purposely to break the Armie; Treaties at the same time with the Queen, on a malignant Interest, and to bring in the <hi>Scots</hi> again; the Souldiers hanged at the Assizes for what they had don as Souldiers; the bringing in the King, whom they had impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session at <hi>Holdenbie,</hi> upon his own, or their Interest, which was all one; and all that apparant transaction for the destruction of the <hi>Parlament-Interest,</hi> the Armie, and all that did adhere to them; how tender were they of making the least extraordinarie attempt for their preservation; till God was pleased in the verie souldierie to rais up an unheard of spirit to stand for Justice, their lives and Liberties, and of the honest Interest also, and the Lord Gen. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> and other their chief Officers intended to bee impeach't as Traitors, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd to repair to them for shelter? (which Providence of God England will never have caus to forget) Did they then tyrannize, or do to anie as was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to bee don to them? let the verie men that thirsted for their bloud speak in this particular.</p>
               <p>When the Boyish Rabble (encouraged by som of the Rabbies) had committed that unparallel'd, and not to bee pardoned force on the Hous of Commons, that the Speaker and manie Members were enforced to repair to the Armie, and presently upon that an Armie raised in <hi>London,</hi> and that garrison'd; the same attempted throughout all England; beeing the beginnings of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther war, and which occasioned the Armie's drawing up to <hi>London,</hi> and their marching thorough it: after that the enemie had most cowardly quit it, did they plunder the Citie, or take one half pennie from them? Did they seclude those members that sate in the Hous acting against them; and appearing a Color of Authoritie for such proceedings? did they turn those Ministers out of the Pulpits that had alarm'd this war? or was there anie Justice don for the bloud that was then shed, (the more I think is there to bee answered for) or the mischiefs that ensued thereupon?</p>
               <p>Did they seclude anie of the Members of <hi>Parlament,</hi> till the sad experience (to saie nothing of what is afore mentioned) of the <hi>Scot's</hi> invasion; the insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections everie where in the year 1648; the breach of the Navie; the delaying the Ordinance for the <hi>Militia;</hi> the invaliditie of that Ordinance; the carrying on of the Treatie at the Isle of <hi>Wight;</hi> the voting the concessions there in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a safe peace; the intention of voting the Armie Traitors, that had fought so gallantly that year also; and to have adjourn'd the Hous, that the King and they might with united force bee able to subdue them; together with a constant <hi>series</hi> of obstructing what concern'd the true Parlament-Interest, and the promoting of the King's, enforc't the putting by of such that had been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118628:10"/>fals to their Trust, that so the remainder, whose hearts were faithful to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and the Common-Interest, might the more roundly prosecute the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Justice on the King (the head and fountain of the first war;) the Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Government to the best advantage of <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>Libertie,</hi> and the <hi>Safetie</hi> of the true Interest, which by enemies abroad, and seeming friends at home, had been put to so manie desperate, and sad extremities; out of which, even through miracle they had been but then delivered; and let anie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screet, and impartial observer of those things judg, whether the <hi>Providence</hi> of of God, and the absolute necessitie of <hi>Publick Safetie,</hi> did not enforce those proceedings; for which, all those that wish well to the great designs of God in this Nation, have caus to bless the Lord; and bee thankful, as a greater mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie then their former deliverances?</p>
               <p>When the Providence of God, in the Justice of this Nation, had brought the King to Execution, and chang'd the Government for the best advantage of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Justice, Libertie and Safetie, how did this generation of men <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viribus</hi> endevor the destruction of this Common-wealth? what mourning was there amongst them for <hi>Tammuz? Ezek.</hi> 8.14. fetching deeper sighs for the King's execution, then the purer Cavileer: what desperate and bitter inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives have been the constant enterteinments of most Congregations from their Pulpits, pressing more the destruction of this Common-wealth, then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the GOspel of Christ, making the Government (what in them laie) to stinck; (shall I saie, amongst the prophane of the Nation?) yea, even in the nostrils of the most truly godly, that by enervating of the sacredness of their Autoritie, the people might bee prepared to take anie opportunitie to root it out: yea, they have fallen into the Malignant Interest; and, with one soul and united endeavors, they have not onely attempted to cast this Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie out of the hearts of the people, but have plotted, contrived, advanc't and compleated a combination of the Scots, and their King, to bring upon this Common-wealth the force of Scotland, and what other parts can contribute towards the war there raised; which they not onely at first brought to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but ever since have assisted to their power, as in the relation of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign before appeareth.</p>
               <p>But how hath the State proceeded with these men? have there been narrow Inquisitions made into the things before mentioned? have anie been made examples of Justice? what a weight of bloud and Treasure lie's upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding, the Lord <hi>Lisle</hi> from Ireland, and delivering all into <hi>Inchiqueen's</hi> hands, who delivered it to the Enemie, and reduced the Parlament's Interest there to the walls of Dublin, which was also besieged? To recover this when England's wars (through them occasioned) could not prevent, not a praier of theirs would go for our forces that went thither; (no, 'twas against their Conscience) no blessing of God for the rare successes given against the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, which confirm's their guilt upon them, and the bloud on their heads:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118628:10"/>What a weight lie's upon the boies, forcing the Hous of Commons, and the raising of an Armie in London, and garrisoning thereof? upon the Treaties with the Queen, and bringing in the Scots? upon the favoring of Insurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and breach of the Navie, not to this daie recovered? upon the Treatie at the Isle of <hi>Wight</hi> (where they made a private agreement with the King); and the endeavoring to hinder Justice from coming upon his head? yea, what a weight lie's on all their practices to destroie this Common-wealth, assoon as it was born? to set the Nation on fire about our ears? to fall into a malignant Interest? and, when their poor Countrie had travelled under nine years bloudie war, to bring the war upon it, that now is at this daie? what a deal of guilt of bloud lie's here? <hi>England's</hi> bloud, <hi>Ireland's,</hi> and <hi>Scotland's</hi> bloud? the guilt of that Familie that God is plucking up by the roots, and that Interest; who is able to stand before God with this weight of guilt and bloud; unless the bloud of Christ wash it away? How can the Justice of man pass by such guilt and bloud without the execution of punishment: I saie, have these things been enquired into, or visited? nay, have they not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in their places to this verie daie? have they not the libertie of their consciences, which they would not grant to others, but endeavored to destroie their bodies for their conscience sake, though their practice had more of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine stamp upon it, then these men's Principles? have they not their verie waie of worship commended by the State to the Nation, though no <hi>jus diviunm</hi> appear's for a Magistratical Coercion to that, or anie other waie of outward worship? have they not the proprietie of their estates, and the protection of that, and their persons, though they make it Conscience and Religion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroie this Government; and this Protection they have as far forth as anie member that sits in Parlament? Have they not their Pulpits, and full libertie to preach the Gospel of Christ, and to live in all godliness and honestie? Or were there ever sharper Laws made against vice and prophaneness? and these things have they not enjoied in a constant <hi>Series</hi> without anie interruption to this verie daie?</p>
               <p>And as for the Armie, with how much bowels and tenderness, have they proceeded towards them? How often have they desired meetings, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, to deal with each other according to the rule of Christ? Witness, amongst other things, the desires for twentie of them to com to <hi>Windsor,</hi> and preach to them; if by anie means there might bee a good understanding; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the Message of the Council of war by M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Peters,</hi> Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> and Major <hi>Cartar,</hi> intreating them to com and sit with them in their Council; see their proceedings, admonish, and direct them; and the manie desires of the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> for that purpose; but they scorned and rejected all, would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther com to <hi>Windsor,</hi> nor the Council of War; nay, when the head Quarters were at London, Cornet <hi>Joyce</hi> and Captain <hi>Beaumount</hi> were sent to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Council, and after that Liev. General <hi>Cromwel,</hi> now Lord General, went
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118628:11"/>himself to desire a union if possible; but all would not do. M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love,</hi> instead of hearing what M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Peters</hi> and Colonel <hi>Okey</hi> spake, railing upon them, said, <hi>Yee are a companie of Hereticks, and Schismaticks, and the curs of God is on you, and will destroie you; I will not have to do with you;</hi> Nor would they discours with the Officers, but at the then Lord General <hi>Fairsax;</hi> where M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Calamie,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Whittaker,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Marshal,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Cauton,</hi> and two more made set speeches for the King, purposely to draw off the said Lord General to give up his Commission, and thereby advantage the King's, and their affairs, touching the Scot's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, and instead of hearkning to these brotherly addresses, have plotted, and don as is afore-mentioned.</p>
               <p>And this hath been the fruit of the Indulgence of the State to them, and their <hi>impunitie</hi> from punishment, even to spread <hi>Religion</hi> upon the face of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:</hi> and the doing of God good service, to bring in the Atheistical and hellish troops of Scots and Malignants upon the peace of this Common-wealth, after that they had prepared the hearts of the people by their pestilent doctrine to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroie this State, and warmed the bloodie and frozen spirits of the Roialists, who seek their destruction, and who, with an united force have caused the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of manie thousands to fall in this War, and how manie more no man know's.</p>
               <p>And yet to preserv one of the chief of these Traitors, what endeavors are there? what sollicitations? yea, after the Parlament, out of their due sens of the blood-shed, the apparent hazard of the Common-wealth, and the destructive principles of these men, had once denied a Repriev to bee put to the question, and upon the question anie pardon?</p>
               <p>Nor are the common sort of men now the persons that dare appear to force the door of a <hi>Repriev</hi> open, when shut by Parlament; but a parcel of fiftie four Ministers who make light of Treasons, are sufficiently bold to present a Petition in the behalf of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love,</hi> for a Repriev; whom to the Parlament, they style <hi>their dear and beloved Brother,</hi> though as yet hee cannot own this Government as the Ordinance of God for good; nor discover the Treasons hee hath known to bee against it, and yet seek's mercie of a State, to whom hee can shew no mercie himself.</p>
               <p>'Tis no marvel that these men appear in this particular (it beeing their first Petition to the Parlament, and therefore deserv's to bee recorded): In regard that the deserts of som of them beg's their own repriev in M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love's,</hi> the wel-wishes that others have to the good successes of his designs, manifested much in their saucie behavior to God and man in that particular, and whom time will shortly discover, all of them, the preservation of that spirit of Dominion, and of Antichrist that lie's in the bottom, and a Papal Privilege of their necks from a Magistratical Execution, in case of future Treasons, and other misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors, and none but these have confidence enough to endeavor the diversion of Justice upon this evil doer.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118628:11"/>
               <p>One would think that of all men (since the whole Tribe seem's to bee gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in this business) the Ministers should have cleared their own reputation, in desiring Justice to bee executed impartially, even upon their own dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to detect rather then to smother such Treasons; and to bee executioners themselvs, rather then Justice should want Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>Moses</hi> said, Who is on the Lord's side? Who? and then gathered to him all the Sons of <hi>Levi;</hi> and hee said; Go in and our through the came, and slaie eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man his Brother, Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, neighbor; and they slew three thousand men that daie. For <hi>Moses</hi> had said, Consecrate your selvs to daie to the Lord, everie one upon his son, and upon his Brother, that hee may he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow upon you a blessing this daie, &amp;c. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.9. Who said unto his Father, and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have not seen him, nor did hee acknowledg his Brethren, nor knew his own Children.</note> the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> once famously did, going throughout the Camp, sparing nor father, Brother, or kinsman; for whose zeal God took them to serv at his Altar, and made with <hi>Levi</hi> a Covenant of salt, that so their care of the safetie of the State that protect's them, their sens of the bloud-shed in this war, and their detestation of these horrid works of darkness might appear; but not a word of these things is crouded in their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and which deserv's <hi>nigro carbone notari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have they compassion to one man? Where is their compassion to a State? their zeal for Justice? for the bloud shed in Scotland, and the sad miseries of this war? Where is their tenderness to the poor people in England, whose bellies do pinch to maintain the forces that stand between destruction and them, to our forces there, the Lord General, and those that have endured the cold and bitter lodgings of that steril Countrie; manie of whose lives it may bee are, ere this breathed forth, for our deliverance from these effects of these Treasons? where is compassion for these? or run's their compassion in one stream onely? certainly it must bee divided, or such Principles cut off from this Common-wealth; otherwise peace will depart from our Israel. But of som of them better things are hoped; and such which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie the Gospel, and the peace and good of this Common-wealth, though beeing found amongst the Birds of prey in the Petition. The first <hi>Partridg</hi> Plea of a dutiful and tender temper, cannot excuse them from the Fowler's answer, and that justly, What do you amongst them? and they must bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to bear the reproof that God doth hereby give them.</p>
               <p>Now that these reflections may not seem too severe, the charge of Treason aggravated beyond what the nature of it will allow, bee pleased soberly to consider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether anie Partie of men, within the jurisdiction of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, assuming to themselvs a supre me power, bee not a most trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent Act of High-Treason, inconsistent with the verie beeing of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth?</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118628:12"/>
               <p n="2">2. Whether any Partie of men, within the jurisdiction of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, taking upon them the power of granting Commissions and Instructions to treat with a Foreign State, and the proclaimed enemie to this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>(viz.) Charls Stuart</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> bee not an assuming to themselvs a supreme power, and a most transscendent Act of high Treason, which strike's at the root of the present Autoritie; it beeing impossible, that two supreme Powers in one Common-wealth can consist.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether anie Partie of men within the jurisdiction of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, taking upon them the power of autorizing persons to treat, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, by virtue of the Commands of <hi>Charls Stuart,</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the declared Traitor to this State, bee not a most transscendent Act of High Treason?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether, upon the conclusion of a Treatie, all the parties therein concern'd are not concluded in everie particular of that Agreement? Then, whether all the Parties concern'd at the late Treatie at <hi>Breda,</hi> are not concluded in that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Treatie, which engageth to assist the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> with force to obtain his Father's dominions in <hi>England?</hi> and then, whether everie such Partie bee not guiltie of the warr in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (the effects thereof) and of all the blood that hath been, or shall bee shed in that warr?</p>
               <p>But, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love,</hi> and his confederates (as hath been proved at the Court) have assumed to themselvs such a supreme power in autorizing by Commission, the Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> of <hi>Parham,</hi> &amp;c. and other enemies and Traitors to this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, upon their own and the secluded members autoritie (which they value to bee better then those at <hi>Westminster</hi>) and of the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> who advised them so to do, to treat with the said King of <hi>Scots,</hi> and the Scottish Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners at <hi>Breda.</hi> (who had proclaimed <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England</hi>) At which Treatie, one Article concluded, was to assist the King with force, to obtain possession of his Father's dominion in <hi>Engl.</hi> this produced the war now in <hi>Scotl.</hi> and all the bloud that hath or shall bee shed, and the miseries that hath or shall ensue thereupon: And not only so, but they were the verie men that brought the King &amp; the <hi>Scots</hi> several times to treat, and at last to agree, as in the relation of the design aforesaid appear's. When the Treatie was at <hi>Breda,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> and his confederates kept private Fasts, for a blessing on the Treatie, and for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it after it was made, and ever since the said agreement; and the King's coming into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the clapping up of som of the Correspondents, they constantly corresponded with the Committees of Estates, and Kirk, and in <hi>Scotl.</hi> have kept their Agents (<hi>Massie</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>) there, have laid waies of intelligence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and gave advice concerning raising Parties in <hi>England, Massie's</hi> marching into <hi>England;</hi> likewise concerning monie, Arms, bringing over foreign Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, Generals, Shipping, &amp;c. All which M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                  <hi>Love</hi> hath held forth to bee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Judgment, Conscience, and the Covenant, and this is the fiftie four Ministers dear and beloved brother, and his transscendent Treasons: the English
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118628:12"/>of all, beeing, That out of <hi>Judgement, Conscience, and the Covenant, everie man ought to seek the subversion of this Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="query">
                  <head>Quere.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHether such Treasons, and Principles, which strike at the verie roots of Autoritie, can receiv pardon or allowance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the apparent hazard of the Common wealth, an injurie to justice, and the leaving the bloud shed in this Warr without expiation?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 35.31, 32, 33. Moreover, yee shall take no satisfaction for the life of a murtherer, but hee shall bee surely put to death: so you shall not pollute the Land wherein you are; for bloud it defileth the Land, and the Land cannot bee cleansed of the bloud that is shed therein, but by the bloud of him that shed it.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To conclude this particular, let everie English man now consider, who occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the first breach amongst the Parlament's friends, and who are the persons that with violence and an implacable spirit have carried it on to this daie; where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to charge the mischiefs, that have ensued upon all the divisions formerly, and the bloud of this present warr, and what ground they have had for such destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive principles and practices; Kindness, bowels, impunitie. The sad miseries and ruines of <hi>England</hi> have been a very smal thing in their eies, they must have their own pride and dominion set up, or <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> must lie in its bloud; all things must bee null, that they pass not, and the worst of waies good enough to attempt it, and tis no sin so to do, because they will have itso; what God hath don before their eies upon the late King for such things, prevail's not with them; no, though the feet of those that carried him forth, stand readie at the door, for som of these condemn'd for treasons: hee would <hi>rule by his Will,</hi> and these will make their <hi>Will a rule,</hi> or <hi>England</hi> or they must rue for it: the later begin's to bee som of their portions, though all their lives they have had to do in these treasons, are a very little satisfaction for the blood that hath been and may bee the portion of this War. Poor England! how little value is put by these upon thy pretious blood, and long desired peace? what will becom of thee after this rate? Our Lord Christ or his Apostles warrant no such thing
<note place="margin">a <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.52.</note>
                     <hi>Put up thy sword, Peter,</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>My Kingdom is not of this world</hi>
                     <note place="margin">b 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24, 25.</note>
                     <hi>The Servant of the Lord must be gentle, meek, merciful,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">c 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3.</note>
                     <hi>no striker, &amp;c.</hi> saith the Apostle; and his weapons,
<note place="margin">d 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 15, &amp;c.</note> Instruction, Exhortation, Reproof, &amp;c. and, <hi>Let no man suffer as a murderer, a thief, an evil doer, or as a busie bodie in other mens matters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118628:13"/>
                  <p>Consider also who hath been, is, the occasion of thy present sufferings, O <hi>England!</hi> and the caus of thy manie pressures and taxations? Warr is that which emptie's thy purs; and want of peace prevent's the relieving of thy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions, and who they are that are the ground therof thou seest. Let not English men rail upon the Parlament, much less let anie take up arms against them, that are forc't to a chargeable cure proportionable to the wound; but look to the hand that give's the wound, and bless God that it is in the hearts of any to applie a remedie. I shall add no further, but upon the serious consideration of the whole, as the Levite said to the men of <hi>Israë,</hi> concerning his Concubine, so say I, Yee men of <hi>England, Consider, and speak your minds, whether any such Treasons have been don or seen in this Nation?</hi> Judges 17.30.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>For the mischiefs that threaten the Common-wealth in all, though what hath been said alreadie may seem enough for this particular, yet give mee leav to add:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the designs herein mentioned are the highest Acts of Treasons, that hath in this generation, or in many ages before been brought to the Bar of Justice, except that of the late Kings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are carried upon the pretens of Covenant, and enforced with a Religious tie on the hearts of manie, who otherwise are truly godlie, and have don good service for the Common-wealth, which make's it the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are Principles generally of the Ministerie of the Nation, whose Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits have served for Trumpets of Sedition and Rebellion, when they should have sounded out the Gospel onely; and these, as they have gathered the hearts of the people against their Governors, so som of them are drawn into the field to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroie this State: no people but such as these could rationally have disturbed the peace of the Common-wealth, (the King's partie and the Scots beeing a dead snake without their warmth) and never will this State bee at peace, whilst their intermedling with State-affairs is not effectually restrained; and herein lie's the great interest of the safetie of the people.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Should not Exemplarie Justice bee don, how will the hearts of men bee set to do mischief? how will people bee encouraged to plot, and design? when will this State bee free from wars and destruction? how will this Generation of men bee emboldned in their Rebellion to this State? The Pulpits can scarce hold them alreadie, the Seat of Government will not shortly bee able to hold those in Autoritie; how will the Justice and Providence of God bee answered, and the ruine that this war hath and may bring upon this Nation and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> and how will men have occasion to hear and fear, and do no more so wickedly?</p>
               <p n="5">5. To what end do wee search into the designs of men, and the Providence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118628:13"/>of God serv to the detection of their works of Darkness, if these go unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished?</p>
               <p n="6">6. What Encouragement shall your Armies have to fight with your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, when those that occasion that war shall bee convict, and yet go unpunish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Every drop of bloud of your Souldiers shed should be as out of your veins, and every hardship as your own.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To what end are the constitutions of humane Societie, if men may refuse to answer to questions upon informations of Treasons when asked? to inform against other Traitors and offenders if required? and to refuse to swear before the Magistrate when by him demanded for the bearing witness against Traitors? such Principles as these nor <hi>Strafford,</hi> nor <hi>Canterbury</hi> held forth; an Act of Parliament was made for their Execution, these have offended many Acts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made, and brought a terrible war upon this Nation; Can a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and these things stand?</p>
               <p>I shall forbear to add farther, everie man's reason from the Premisses will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily draw what conclusions do arise: there is a rare opportunitie put into the hand of the State, to curb and exstirpate the licentiousness of the Clergie, in what concern's the affairs of the State; likewise to let men know at what rate they shall buie their Treasons, and hereby to establish the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; the Lord grant that in this our daie wee may know the things that concern our peace.</p>
               <p>Upon the consideration of the whole, to mee it is great matter of amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to see men, good men, men that give sentence as to life and death, to bee turning everie Stone, and so earnestly soliciting for favor to these Traitors, when they thereby shew what little sens of the Common safetie, the bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, and the executing of Justice is upon their heart; were the war brought home to their own doors, the swords at their throats, their friends and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions weltring in their bloud; their Estates and friends plundred, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, their houses and Cities burnt to the ground; their Virgins and Matrons ravish't, and deflour'd, and all manner of wickedness acted upon them, and before their eies; were they but forc't to eat the peas the horses do leav on the ground, and the intrails of the sheep, which is becom the poor <hi>Scotch</hi> people's portion; or indure what ours have in <hi>Scotland</hi> with bread and water (if they could have it) in midst of winter, when they lie in the field, in the rain, wet, and cold, where they have nor fire nor shelter (all which hath been the portion of our dear friends, who are as precious in the eies of the Lord as our selvs, or anie of those for whom these are advocates) they would then bee of another minde; but whilst wee can injoie our beds, wives, Families, offices, riches, without the nois of war, or the sence of the purs (which manie thousands feel in the Contribution for the mainteining of these forces) And have not the grim faces of slaughtred men, and their famished Familie staring us in the face; wee foolishly prefer two or three men's persons (the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118628:14"/>occasioners of these things) before the lives of thousands, and the sastie of a Common-wealth, and which is more, the serving of God in the doing of Justice.</p>
               <p>'Tis strange to see how men dare to appear in the behalf of such Traitors, nay, speak for them in places of Eminencie, these things will have a sad reckoning one daie; when your Fathers executed Justice (said the Prophet to the Jews) was it not well with them? certainly Treason must bee a rougher thing then to bee thus handled: or the head of the Common-wealth will bee laid in the grave; and for such persons, their language seem's to bee after the manner of <hi>Ashdod,</hi> and their hearts beeing devided, they shall not prosper.</p>
               <p>But blessed bee the Lord there bee manie faithful Patriots of a Presbyterian judgment, who defie these works of darkness, and who testifie against them; and whom these men falsly intitle to their Treasons, by using the name of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian partie, and also manie thousand other, more also I trust will bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc't; when the Ministers mists are from before their eies.</p>
               <p>To conclude, I can appeal to the Lord, that in this I have no bitterness or prejudice to anie man's person, onely out of a deep sens of <hi>Common-safetie.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light not in the blood of anie, much less of a State. But seeing what practises there are in the world, and what sad issues may proceed from thence, how few also tender common-safetie in this shaking time, I have been constreined to this, wherein very much more might bee said, and having born my testimonie I am satisfied; desiring rather to fall with Justice, then stand without it; and the Lord do with this discours as it seemeth good unto him.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 28, 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Praie for the peace of Jerusalem, they shall prosper that love it.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Psal. 122.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>Shalt thou reign becaus thou closest thy self in Cedar? did not thy father eat and drink, and do Judgment, and Justice, and then it was well with him?</p>
                  <p>Hee Judged the caus of the poor and needie, then it was well with him: was not this to know mee, saith the Lord?
<bibl>
                        <hi>Jer. 22.15.16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <q>If these should hold their peace the stones should immediately crie out.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 19.40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>